Chapter 102, A Bower in the Aridities.
Hitherto in descriptively treating of the sperm whale, I have chiefly dwelt
upon the marvels of his outer aspect, or separately and in detail, upon some few
interior structural features. But to a large and thorough sweeping
comprehension of him, it behooves me now to unbutton him still further, and
untagging the points of his hose, unbuckling his guarders, and casting
loose the hooks and eyes of the joints of his innermost bones, set him before
you in his ultimatum, that is to say, in his unconditional skeleton. But how now,
Ishmael, how is it that you, a mere orarsman in the fishery, pretend to know
aught about the subterranean parts of the whale? Did Arudite stub mounted upon
your capstand, deliver lectures on the anatomy of the citation, and by help of
the windless, hold up a specimen ri for exhibition? Explain thyself, Ishmael.
Can you land a full-grown whale on your deck for examination as a cook dishes a
roast pig? Surely not. A veritable witness have you hitherto been, Ishmael.
But have a care how you seize the privilege of Jonah alone, the privilege
of discoursing upon the joists and beams, the rafters, ridgepoles,
sleepers, and underpinnings making up the framework of the Leviathan, and be
like of the tallow vats, dairy rooms, butteries, and cheeseries in his bowels.
I confess that since Jonah, few whalemen have penetrated very far beneath the
skin of the adult whale. Nevertheless, I have been blessed with an opportunity to
dissect him in miniature.
In a ship I belonged to, a small cub sperm whale was once bodily hoisted to
the deck for his poke or bag to make sheaths for the barbs of the harpoons
and for the heads of the lances. Think you I let that chance go without using
my boat hatchet and jack knife, and breaking the seal and reading all the
contents of that young cub.
And as for my exact knowledge of the bones of the Leviathan in their gigantic
fullgrown development, for that rare knowledge, I am indebted to my late
royal friend Tranquo, King of Tran, one of the Aridities, for being at Tran years ago, when
attached to the trading ship Day of Alers. I was invited to spend part of
the Arcadian holidays with the Lord of Tran at his retired Palm Villa at
Pupella, a seaside Glenn not very far distant from what our sailors called
Bamboo Town, his capital.
Among many other fine qualities, my royal friend Tranquo, being gifted with
a devout love for all matters of barbaric verto, had brought together in
Pupella whatever rare things the more ingenious of his people could invent,
chiefly carved woods of wonderful devices, chiseled shells, inlaid spears,
costly paddles, aromatic canoes, and all these distributed among whatever natural
wonders the wonder freighted tribute render thundering waves had cast upon
his shores. Chief among the latter was a great sperm whale, which after an
unusually long raging gale, had been found dead and stranded, with his head
against a coconut tree, whose plumage-like tufted droopings seemed his
verdant jet. When the vast body had at last been stripped of its fathom deep in
foldings, and the bones became dust dry in the sun, then the skeleton was
carefully transported up the Pupella Glenn, where a grand temple of lordly
palms now sheltered it.
The ribs were hung with trophies. The vertebrae were carved with arceadian
annals in strange hieroglyphics. In the skull, the priest kept up an
unextinguished aromatic flame, so that the mystic head again sent forth its
vapory spout. While suspended from a bow, the terrific lower jaw vibrated
over all the devotees like the hairhung sword that so a frighted damocles.
It was a wondrous sight. The wood was green as mosses of the icy glenn. The
trees stood high and hotty, feeling their living sap. The industrious earth
beneath was as a weaver's loom with a gorgeous carpet on it. Whereof the
ground vine tendrils formed the warp and woof and the living flowers the figures.
All the trees with all their laden branches, all the shrubs and ferns and
grasses, the message carrying air. All these unceasingly were active. Through
the lacings of the leaves the great sun seemed a flying shuttle weaving the
unweed vure. Oh, busy weaver, unseen weaver, pause one word, wither flows the
fabric. What palace may it deck?
Wherefore all these ceaseless toilings speak, weaver, stay thy hand, but one
single word with thee. Nay, the shuttle flies, the figures float from forth the
loom. The fresh rushing carpet forever slides away. The weaver God, he weaves,
and by that weaving is he deafened, that he hears no mortal voice. And by that
humming, we too who look on the loom are deafened. And only when we escape it
shall we hear the thousand voices that speak through it. For even so it is in
all material factories. The spoken words that are inaudible among the flying
spindles, those same words are plainly heard without the walls bursting from
the opened casements. Thereby have villainies been detected. Ah mortal,
then be heedful, for so in all this den of the great worlds loom, thy subtlest
thinkings may be overheard afar.
Now amid the green life restless loom of that arcadedian wood, the great white
worshipped skeleton lay lounging, a gigantic idler. Yet as the ever woven,
verdant warp and woof intermixed and hummed around him, the mighty idler
seemed the cunning weaver, himself all woven over with the vines, every month
assuming greener, fresher vir, but himself a skeleton. Life folded death,
death trellised life, the grim god wived with youthful life, and begat him curly-headed glories.
Now when, with the royal tranqu I visited this wondrous whale, and saw the
skull and altar, and the artificial smoke ascending from where the real jet
had issued, I marveled that the king should regard a chapel as an object of veru.
He laughed. But more I marveled that the priest should swear that smoky jet of
his was genuine. To and fro I paced before this skeleton, brushed the vines
aside, broke through the ribs, and with a ball of arcaded twine, wandered,
eddied long amid its many winding shaded colonades and arbors. But soon my line
was out, and following it back, I emerged from the opening where I
entered. I saw no living thing within.
Not was there but bones.
Cutting me a green measuring rod, I once more dived within the skeleton. From
their arrow slit in the skull, the priest perceived me taking the altitude
of the final rib. How now? They shouted.
Darst thou measure this our god? That's for us. I priests. Well, how long do you
make him then? But here upon a fierce contest rose among them, concerning feet
and inches. They cracked each other's sconces with their yard sticks. The
great skull echoed, and seizing that lucky chance, I quickly concluded my own
ad measurements. These ad measurements I now propose to set before you. But
first, be it recorded that in this matter, I am not free to utter any
fancied measurement I please, because there are skeleton authorities you can
refer to to test my accuracy. There is a Leviathanic museum, they tell me, in
Hull, England, one of the whaling ports of that country, where they have some
fine specimens of finbacks and other whales. Likewise, I have heard that in
the Museum of Manchester in New Hampshire, they have what the proprietors call the only perfect
specimen of a Greenland or river whale in the United States. End quote.
Moreover, at a place in Yorkshire, England, Burton Constable by name, a
certain Sir Clifford Constable has in his possession the skeleton of a sperm
whale, but of moderate size, by no means of the full-grown magnitude of my
friend, King Tranquos.
In both cases, the stranded whales to which these two skeletons belonged were
originally claimed by their proprietors upon similar grounds. King Tranquo
seizing his because he wanted it, and Sir Clifford because he was lord of the
sceneries in those parts. Sir Clifford's whale has been articulated throughout,
so that like a great chest of drawers, you can open and shut him in all of his
bony cavities, spread out his ribs like a gigantic fan, and swing all day upon
his lower jaw. Locks are to be put upon some of his trap doors and shutters, and
a footman will show round future visitors with a bunch of keys at his
side. Sir Clifford thinks of charging tuppens for a peep at the whispering
gallery in the spinal column, 3 pence to hear the echo of the hollow of his
cerebellum, and six pence for the unrivaled view from his forehead.
The skeleton dimensions I shall now proceed to set down are copied verbatim
from my right arm where I had them tattooed, as in my wild wanderings at
that period, there was no other secure way of preserving such valuable
statistics. But as I was crowded for space, and wished the other parts of my
body to remain a blank page for a poem I was then composing, at least what
untattoed parts might remain, I did not trouble myself with the odd inches, nor
indeed should inches at all enter into a congenial ad measurement of the whale.